the person who's thought we're going to
examine today
is usually considered one of the most
important philosophers of the 17th
century But the irony of that is this
that by trade and by even desire
he was not strictly speaking a
philosopher philosophy was something of
an avocation for him something he
dabbled in more or less nevertheless he
made some dramatic contributions to the
history of theoretical thought
his name is Gottfried Wilhelm leibniz
and I'll write his name on the board
because
it's not one that you just automatically
assume you can spell this is a z by the
way l-e-i-b-n-i-z
German philosopher who liked Descartes
had been educated in the Scholastic
tradition of the Roman Catholic Church
one of his claims to fame historically
is that he shares
the historic Accolade for being the
inventor of calculus with Newton
but he was a first-rate world-class
mathematician noticed that that was also
true of Descartes and it was true of
Pascal whom we'll look at later God
willing but in any case
leibniz is noted basically for three
things in as a as a full as a
mathematician
he also became well enough known and was
kind of a people person and was
introduced into the world of diplomacy
and he tried very hard to heal the
breach between Roman Catholicism and
protestantism he was a conciliatory
person and he was looking for ways to
bring Unity out of conflict and that was
true not only at the political realm or
in the ecclesiastical realm but also in
the philosophical and mathematical
sphere he kept coming back to his own
mathematical paradigms in order to find
rational solutions to problems that had
become in many cases quite emotional and
he also had the desire as car as the
Disciples of Descartes did to
reconstruct theology so that the new
science
which was more and more embracing a
mechanistic view of the universe
would not displace God
and so he wanted to develop a way of
making God necessary to the scientific
theories of his day
now he didn't embrace occasionalism
as the French Disciples of Descartes did
but he developed a very elaborate theory
of metaphysics
that is interesting virtually no one
accepts it today but it's interesting
and it's called his system of monad
ology
and that's one of the Innovations for
which he is famous
the second Innovation for which he is
famous
is the development of what is called the
law
of pre-established
Harmony
but that for which he's perhaps most
famous is for his delicate theodicy
I'm going to go over these quickly today
and hope I don't cause you to swim in
the soup of confusion I'm going to be
very brief about this first point
because of all of the aspects of leibniz
thought the one that is most complex and
most difficult to handle in brief is his
whole system of thought called
monadology
in his understanding of reality
he believed that the world was made up
and all things were made up of tiny
little units
of
life or of reality
that again had very strange
characteristics to them
and as I said that's about all I'm going
to say about it except that these
individual units or monads about which
he theorized had no
secondary causality between them
they had no secondary causality between
them now remember what we mean by
secondary causality the idea that one
force imparts uh energy or Force to
something else
but these tiny little
units of which everything is made or in
each one was kind of a microcosm of the
whole universe
and each one had a kind of ability to be
alive or to have what he called petite
perceptions you are a perceiving being
you think you see you taste you touch
you smell and so on and you have a
highly developed sense of Consciousness
and your ability to think and reflect
upon things but for aliveness the whole
world is alive because the whole world
is made up of these little monads each
monad at least has vague simple basic
perceptions
of the world
so it's not all that far from the
American Indians idea that everything is
alive including rocks and so on uh this
is one of the things that prompted
Edward's question uh later what do
sleeping rocks dream of you know they
were having their own petite perceptions
but in any course his answer was nothing
but in any case that where the
monetology comes in to our consideration
of this whole question of causality is
at this point
he believes
that from all eternity
God who creates everything on the basis
of these units of being called monads
programs each one of these individual
units
with their perceptions with their
thoughts with whatever they had
from all eternity
so again though the each monad does not
interact with each other monad by
imparting any kind of secondary
causality to them
but nevertheless the Relationships by
which these virtually infinite number of
monads coalesce and operate together and
make up reality as we see it are all
done by a sort of computer chip that was
put into each one of them by the Creator
at the beginning of time
so again the difference between this and
the occasionalist was the occasionalists
have God intervening at every second to
exercise his divine power
and they denied secondary causes
well there's also a kind of denial of
secondary causality here with leibniz
and again putting back all power to God
but it's not that God is intervening
every second along the way but this was
his form of scientific predestination
not a blind determinism of blind
impersonal forces but a theological
predestination that's built into
everything that takes place in the
universe
so that the Universe for him is not a
mechanical system it's a theological
system
again he is trying to rescue God from
being
displaced by
physical science now it's the third item
that I'm most interested in speaking
about today with respect to alignments
because leibniz produces for us one of
the most famous
theological theodices of all time
the term theodicy
is a term that's made up of two Roots
there is the Greek word Theos which
means
God which we get the word theology
and the word dick iOS or dickasune which
as the word for justness or
righteousness in Greek
and so a theodicy is an intellectual
attempt
to justify God
or to State it in another way a theodicy
is a justification of God
well why would God ever need to be
justified
well the big problem in theology
at and in philosophy is the problem of
evil
if one is going to affirm the existence
of God and attribute to that God who is
the creator of all things the attribute
of goodness
then the basic question is how can a
good God
have a world
where evil exists if God is perfect why
is his handiwork so imperfect I think
we've all wrestled at some time over the
question of the origin of evil where did
Evil come from how did Evil
begin in history
I remember as a brand new Christian I
hadn't thought about that at all and one
day I was playing ping pong in the
basement of the Freshman dormitory and I
was playing my mind was engrossed in a
ping-pong game and Oliver wants it hit
me like a ton of bricks you believe in
God but
there's so much evil in the world
there's so much wrong in the world how
could that happen How could a good God
allow bad things to coexist with him
so as soon as you raise that question
about evil
you're then if you affirm the existence
of God you're now faced with the
question of justifying a good God for
creating a universe that is Fallen
some have called this the Achilles heel
of the Christian faith and the most
difficult theological problem we face
all right well let's look at how leibniz
approached this question in brief
first of all in his approach to the
question he made a distinction among
three distinct types of evil
first of all there is what he called
metaphysical evil
and I'll give a definition of that
metaphysical evil is something akin to
the way Plato thought
metaphysical evil means some
imperfection
of being in the universe
metaphysical evil would be
the lack of pure perfect being
that is basic to anything that is finite
only an infinite being has metaphysical
Perfection according to the philosophers
anything that's finite anything that's
changing anything that's in a state of
flux anything that has the category that
we've talked about many times already of
becoming
is not as high a level of being as pure
being or as Supreme Being so that only
pure being or Supreme Being
Eternal perfect being would uh be
perfectly
metaphysically good
and anything again that is changing
finite derived dependent contingent and
so on would be a lower level of being so
it is called metaphysical evil now I'm
going to put quotes around that word
evil because what that means simply is
that it is imperfect it is less in the
fullness of being than God
now the second kind of evil that leibniz
delineated was what he calls physical
evil
now what he means by physical evil
is
disease
natural catastrophes or calamities like
earthquakes fires floods volcanic
eruptions all of those things by which
nature can wreak havoc on the inhabited
people of this world those are called by
him physical evil they bring harm
physically to us and to the world
so that's physical evil
then the third category
again I'm going to put quotes around the
word evil
the third category is the category of
moral evil
now remember when we started this
and we said if God is good
how could he create a world
where there's so much evil usually what
we're thinking about when we think about
evil there is we're thinking about moral
evil
but we also worry about those
catastrophic events that take place in
this world that insurance companies are
still fond of describing as quote acts
of God
the flood the tornado the earthquake and
so on that bring
unbelievable misery and pain to the
world
and so you also even if we
didn't have such a thing as moral evil
among ourselves we would still ask the
question about God's character about
creating a universe where all these bad
things happen
remember this was one of the basic
questions that the disciples came to
Jesus about during his Earthly Ministry
when the word had come out about the
Temple of had been under construction
that it fell on these innocent people
and then the pilate had mingled the
blood of the uh worship blood of the
sacrifices with of the worshipers with
the blood of the sacrifice and the
slaughter that we hear of only in that
instance in the New Testament and
basically the question that the
disciples are raising is
how could God allow these things to
happen I mean here are these people
minding their own business walking down
the street
and all of a sudden this Temple Falls
over and it crushes him to death it was
a physical accident
nobody intended for the temple to fall
or the tower to fall
it was an act of nature or a physical
consequences where
uh nobody
pushed the tower over on top of these
people
so
how can a good God allow
Vesuvius to erupt and bury the city of
Pompeii in volcanic ash
Where's God in all of this
of course Jesus answers the question
unless you repent you shall all likewise
perish
because following the Old Testament the
presence of physical evil the presence
of death the presence of disease the
presence of conflict in the creation is
all tied into the moral evil of human
beings that is part of the consequences
of the fall but that's another approach
because if we say that we still have to
ask where does this come from where does
the moral evil come
well the way
that leibniz approach this
as I said was first he distinguished
among the three different types of evil
and then tried to posit a relationship
between each one of these
that is to say
again he still has his monetology theory
is that
moral evil flows out of physical evil
and
physical evil and moral evil both flow
out of metaphysical evil that is to say
they are necessary consequences of a
metaphysically imperfect creation
that is since we are finite
out of our finitude comes physical
weaknesses
and out of both our finite status and
our physical weaknesses come our moral
failures
and then he went on to say
that God is absolved in all absolved in
all of this because
when God created the universe
he had
a virtually I say virtually infinite
number of possible worlds he could have
created
I say virtually because there's one kind
of world God even God could not have
created
God would not have been able to create a
metaphysically perfect God
because for God to create a
he would have to create another God
but that even God can't create another
God
why not because the second God would
still be a creature the second God would
be dependent on the first God for its
very existence
so that you can't have God creating
another God all God can create are
creatures that's the nature of creation
so God cannot impart to his creature his
own self-existent
Eternal being
now with that given
and if God is going to create he knows
at the beginning that he can't create
another God so he can create various
different types of universes and he has
again a virtually infinite number of
types of finite universes he creates
now God being good is naturally
going to create
the best
model that he could possibly create
because if he has the option of creating
Model A or model B and model A is more
perfect than model B or to put it the
other way model B is more imperfect or
evil than Model A God would not be good
to choose the second model and if he
were really good he would choose the
first model
and so obviously being all wise and all
righteous God selected the best world he
could possibly create
an ideal world as it were
now you've probably heard the expression
that we are living in the best of all
possible worlds
that sentiment that idea the best of all
possible worlds finds its roots in this
theodicy of leibniz now
you've also probably heard of voltaire's
famous little work Candide many of you
had to read it when you were in college
and it tells the story of this Dr pan
gloss who seems to be a bumbling idiot
because he naively assumes that he's
living in a world that is the best of
all possible worlds and this was written
after a major
Calamity beset Europe the Lisbon
earthquake of that time was more
devastating I guess than the San
Francisco earthquake in our own day
and again people because of the
devastation of the Lisbon earthquake
we're asking this question afresh
Where's God in all of this how could God
allow this to happen and
Voltaire cynically looked at the work of
uh of of leibniz and said you know he's
as an idiot Dr pangloss here walking
around with his head in the clouds
thinking that this is the best of all
possible worlds and that even though
we're not Gods we can conceive of a much
better world than we're presently living
in
and not only that the scriptures
themselves talk about a world that will
be better in the renovations and that's
the Fatal problem from the Christian
perspective of this theodicy is that
it's on a collision course with the
biblical story of creation and a fall
and of renovation
and it does the the the New Testament or
the Old Testament does not look at moral
evil as a necessary consequence of
finitude
that's the critical point because in our
modern day
there are many many theologians and
psychologists who
eliminate
responsibility of real moral evil
saying that we just do what comes
naturally that sin is a necessary
consequence
of being a finite creature we are Human
After All to ER is human to forgive is
divine
and so from a Christian Viewpoint this
attempt to justify God
fails because it first of all doesn't
justify God and second of all doesn't
square at all with the view of moral
evil that we find In classical
Christianity